It's 7-8, I'll be here. I I.
Catalogue.
Mm.
OK, I will use.
Right.
We.
Uh, today we uh start. Um.
I'll check the account.
No, no collaborative thing.
OK.
So today we will start the exploration of.
The so-called higher order programming,
OK.
I'm generated in your mind the idea that
the only thing that is characterized by
the program is the ability to have
function that can be returned.
As a result of a functioning location,
and this allows you to treat the function
as values,
which of course is a main trait of higher
order programming, but it's not.
The only point.
So my goal for today is to break some of
the assumption you have in your C
oriented mind,
because at the end of the day most of the
program programming language we use a
syntax that is derived.
To some extent from C,
C++ and then Java and then C# and then
JavaScript and Python.
I mean at the end of the day with
variance,
but basically the root of most of the
programming language used today.
It stays in the C syntax,
but it is not the only available
programming language out there style.
There are other languages, some of them.
Like Haskell are research languages.
Haskell has been designed to study
programming languages.
It was an experiment originally started
by Simon Clayton Johns.
And it it has a lot of interesting
features,
but it is really for research purpose.
But there are also programming languages
that have been used.
Many rounds into industrial projects.
One of these is for sure.
MLML has been already mentioned.
I did mention it yesterday when we were
talking about the your grants and I show
you the very small line.
And it is for many years it was popular
in the universities in a form,
in a public form implementation known as.
Oh, Camel.
Which where the O stands for object
because the original ML didn't have
support for object oriented programming.
And the last iteration which is supported
by an industrial player which is
Microsoft,
it is known as F sharp and F sharp is
basically an ML port for net.
So technically if you want to program.
ML today you can use F# and and and you
have mostly ML.
The object model is clearly different
from.
For subtleties,
I mean of course you have inheritance
fields etcetera,
but of course it has been adapted to the
net so that you can interact and use all
the libraries from net in a seamless way,
which is a good thing.
And the and it has been used really
heavily in finance.
So the largest deployment that I knew,
I've been one of the leaders of the
community at some point,
but I mean in the recent year.
I use it less and less,
so I'm just an old man that has a lot of
memories about that.
And I can I will share also not just
today,
but when we will move along into the
runtime, I was lucky enough to witness.
Is the first bootstrap of the F# compiler
on dotnet. It was 2001.
So there are a lot of interesting aspects
in the way these things are done, but.
The the largest deployment I think is
still in Credit Suisse where they have
more than 2,000,
000 lines of code in production for real
production on on F sharp.
So it's a it's a real world programming
language and I will say that.
In the if you look at Python, Lua,
JavaScript and I can go on and on and on
that you will find basically the same
idea,
same programming language with slightly
different syntaxes some.
Done well, such as JavaScript,
others done less well, such as Python.
But at the end of the day,
the overall structure of the language is
the same.
The decision about typing are similar.
So in this world where everybody was
reinventing their own language by simply
mimicking an existing one,
when F# came out,
a lot of people passionate about
programming language implementation and
experimentation.
Naturally convert into that space.
And in fact,
if you look around the F# community has
produced a lot of interesting research in
programming languages because it was the
fun programming language.
Around.
And so I think in this respect it has
been quite influential. In particular,
I will say that it was one of the
language that made again popular the
keyword let.
So when F# came out,
let it was not even allowed in JavaScript.
Nowadays we use it to write let something.
It made popular asynchronous programming
thanks to a feature that is embedded into
the language that we will discuss.
And it is still unique in one feature
that it makes really appealing,
for instance in finance.
So in finance became popular because
there was a functional programming
language,
an interpreter one that was called Open F.
It was 2014 and it came up and all the
London finance was based on this open F
At some point someone found a really,
really bad bug in security in finance and
everybody was cared about.
This this bug and so they look around.
Is there a functional programming
language that we can use to go out from
open F which is broken and Microsoft was
developing F sharp was embedded in in
Visual Studio so there was industrial
support so.
Debugger and everything and so they
basically moved on F#.
So it was partly due to to this fortunate
for Microsoft coincidence, so.
I was saying there is still a unique
feature of the language which is abstract
is the only language out there.
So this is if you want somehow out of
scope.
Uh,
but it's the only programming language
that has the full measure. Uh.
Metric algebra implemented.
By this I mean that you can write a code
where you can label numbers with metres,
seconds, any dimension.
And then if you divide meters by seconds,
you will get meters per second and the
statically the programming language type
checks whether you're summing up.
Numbers with the same measure attached to
them.
And in this respect there was Andrew
Kennedy was the author of the of this of
the paper.
Also it was published in some journal
that discussed how to implement and
statically type check.
Like unit of measure attached to numbers
and this is very useful in physics in in
finance because clearly you may be tent
if you if you sum 2 double numbers any
programming language will allow you to
sum.
Double numbers,
but if you can label numbers with the
unit of measure,
you can avoid the significant errors,
especially in domains where numbers are
aware.
So the risk of summing up the numbers
that are incompatible is very high.
So just that.
To showcase.
And you generate on F sharp example of
unit of measure user show meters and
seconds.
So.
You will get a full.
If the network helps in the meantime,
I mean as I was saying that is just a
note which I think is useful to know,
but I mean.
That is not the reason because you pick
up a particular programming language.
So how can you use F sharp?
For those of you that are interested in
in trying the language,
you simply install.net Framework,
the SDK you look for.
Net SDK framework which now is multi.
I mean it's open source multi platform.
It runs from Raspberry Pi upwards so you
can run where you want and.
The F# compiler is part of the
distribution,
so you got the FC FSC command that allows
you to compile the F# files and you also
get the F# interactive.
Which is basically a breadful environment
where you type,
you can type in FR statements and
evaluate them and you get the results and
so you can interactively evaluate things
so.
Uh.
Here you see the examples.
So basically there is a special syntax.
Uh.
The square brackets have been introduced
by C# as an annotation and has been
retained by many languages.
So in F# square brackets were deeply
overloaded, so in F# you use.
Open square brackets and angles bracket
to to start the annotation and the close.
close the right angle bracket and close
the square bracket to close the
annotation.
Then you say type M type is a keyword in
F sharp,
so type is how you introduce types in the
language.
In this case you don't give a definition.
Because you the type has been annotated
as a measure.
So this means this type M should be
considered the the unit of measure of the
in in this context.
So you have also the types S that is the
second.
And as you can see then you can evaluate
100 metres, 9.
558 seconds and and then you can say OK
these distance over time.
And then in F sharp you got print FN
which is inspired from C where you can
provide the format string and the
arguments and and that's it. OK,
so I mean fairly easy.
And so if if you evaluate,
you will get the the the meters per
second from using bolt in this example
generated. OK, so I mean as I was saying.
Keep it there.
So at some point we when we will talk
about types, maybe this will pop up,
but I'm pretty sure you can be easily
convinced that you can statically check
types and then get rid of the annotations
so that at runtime you just get numbers.
OK, so.
I'm confident that you will not be
surprised by the fact that you can
statically verify the text of the program
to ensure that everything is behaving
properly. OK, so if I.
Paste this.
In uh.
In the F sharp interactive,
I get the evaluation with all the numbers,
of course now speed.
And be evaluated because in the abstract
interactive all the environment is
preserved.
Um.
OK, now let's move over. Can I zoom in?
Yes.
And all.
First of all,
this is not a course about F#,
so I will use F#.
I will explain you the syntax which is
relevant.
If you have any question about the syntax
I will use,
but I mean this is advanced programming.
My goal is to showcase interesting
programming buttons.
And elements of programming languages.
Otherwise I mean it would become at first
about many programming language which is
not the.
The case,
I will take the opportunity to start
exploring a programming language that is
likely you don't know,
so that you can start also witnessing the
process.
Of how can I learn something about the
programming language? I don't know.
I mean,
I'm in trouble even in understanding the
syntax of the language. OK,
so how many of you ever ever programming
ML or or Ocaml or F# or?
OK.
That one is OK, so so.
No.
Any of you knows about curing?
And I'm curry.
I see him knocking and I'm not attruding
you because you nodded.
So the first thing,
so when you approach a programming
language like this,
so most of the class knows about,
so I won't exaggerate in in guessing.
When you approach a programming language,
a new programming language,
you have to understand whether it's we
said whether it's a compiled.
Or interpreted. F# is a compiled language.
In fact,
the F# interactive simply compiles and
execute the line.
So in functional programming language,
this is easy because in a functional
programming language everything is an
expression.
OK,
and so functional programming languages
are really easy to have an interactive
execution environment,
even if they are compiled because there
are no,
I mean in C you need to declare the main.
And the main is the entry point and then
you have to go around and execute all the
functions in programming languages.
In functional programming languages the
habit is everything is an expression.
Then you have also the ability to declare,
give meaning to names.
But the whole nature of the language
remains expression oriented.
And so typically you can evaluate the
line by line or statement by statement
without much problems.
So something which is not true in C
oriented programming languages where you
have a lot of blocks.
If you want to properly execute for
instance C#,
technically you should evaluate one file
at a time because you you got the
namespace statement which contains
everything.
So if you start evaluating only the
classes inside,
technically it's not equivalent because
you are.
Skipping the namespace block which is
enclosing all the file. OK,
so first of all it is compiled even
though I can write let.
Uh.
And is equal 1 + 2 in the interactive
column, column,
column is the end of the statement and so
you ask for the evaluation. Here I.
Uh wrote uh uh.
Let N is equal 1 + 2 and by the fact that
I assign the result of a sum of 2
integers to N,
the language inferred that in N has to be
of type.
Integer.
So this is now common in most of the
programming of static type programming
languages.
The fact that we start using letter var
name equal and the type of expression
implicitly become the type of the value.
Table the type inference that had been
introduced for the first time in ML.
It's much more complicated and the.
The language is able to resolve also
non-trivial form of of inferences.
So we will get back to that later because
I need to introduce a few other things
before that.
One of the first things that unsettles
the FR programmer in the beginning is the
fact that that you can define a function
such as.
This and then say OK,
let add X given X&
Y and the definition is X + y, but if you.
Was C# or Java or it will be like this
name location,
but if I try to evaluate it I get an
error. Many of you have already.
Use the ML so you know that the proper
way to invoke is by saying at 1/2.
And the result is 3. First of all,
anyone has an idea of why we can't use
the phrases?
Why this?
Add 1-2 is not.
Right.
So the reason is that brace where you use
it. So first of all,
the root of the language was lambda
calculus and lambda calculus was from
mathematics and the use was different in.
In things in mathematics,
and so it was more natural than you may
perceive today in AC oriented world.
But the other reason,
and it's a practical one,
is that the language supports the tuple
types. So tuple is.
Um.
A multi field value.
There has no name because in a Java world
you are using that every type has a name
in in in.
In ML you can combine types and not only
by inheritance which which is an
operation.
I have a type and the inheritance.
If you create a new type which inherits
from the base type,
you are using a particular operator.
Of the types algebra which is the is F.
So it's OK all the values of the derived
class can be used where a value of the
base class is expected. This is basically.
A type constructor. OK,
type constructor is an operation that
given a set of one or more basic types,
returns you with a new type in the system
in.
Uh, ML you have.
And it's expressed with the the star,
the cross product essentially.
Because if you think when I say int,
type int,
I'm I'm basically giving you a set,
the set of integers.
Right. And so.
In mathematics,
when you have a pair XY in the in the
Cartesian space, it's the cross product.
In fact,
if you remember from the first year,
the RN set is the Cartesian product of of
N times.
Of the real numbers.
So basically that is exactly that that
operation.
It's the cross product of all in this
case of the integer values.
Of course I can say 1A and in this case
the type.
Oh yeah, I'm sorry, one.
A and in this case the type will be the
cross.
So this particular pair is of type cross
product at the integer and strings so.
Tattles were really popular during the
70s.
How many of you,
apart from having been enforced using ML
in the second year,
how many of you ever ever used tuples in
in your programming?
Less.
So why are you using tuples?
Why? I mean why? Why you said OK,
I have to create A2 dimensional point
structure in my program.
Why are you are using a pair instead of
creating a class that equal point to D?
You can always create a class.
So what your colleague is suggesting.
So basically when I write 1.
2 I in general I if I am if I'm in C# or
in Java I can say class public class.
Point and with two even public fields
because I'm lazy,
I don't want to have accessors so that's
OK and the 1st is of type int and 2nd is
of type int.
Then I want to create I I say new point.
I mean I'm not going to evaluate here,
but I mean I will say like this.
The the point and then I I can pass it
around and I can access like let's say if
P is a point, I can say P dot X&
P dot Y are the two components if you see
what I mean. OK,
so in traditional programming.
Traditional in the 90s object where
object orientation were dominant,
everything was transformed into create a
class and then use the class dot notation
to access the fields. OK if you want to.
Pass around your program some structure
which which has multiple fields.
You simply create an object,
you pass around the object,
and with that you get all the values you
want passing around. That's correct.
Yeah, you have the records.
Pascal you didn't have the objects and
clutter records exactly from the same
board exactly because the first
programming language introducing at the
early operation was similar.
With object, but for the 80s,
Pascal introduced structures which was a
similar concept without the methods and
the only form of objects.
Was the model in in Pascal?
There was the idea that you have a
private state in the model before having
full object orientation. But in any case,
what your colleague was trying to stay is.
A name in your programming language is
expensive.
It's a a notion that is difficult to
quantify.
But if you think of software engineering
of the program,
every name has to be documented,
has to be defined somewhere.
You have to write the meaning of every
single field, etcetera.
So when you said that it's too heavy,
you will basically say come on,
I I just need a pairs of integer.
Why should I define a class?
And by the way,
if I define a class I should name point.
If I want to create a point,
then I need another pair structure with
two integer fields,
but I can't reuse point type because
point is point is not something else.
I don't want to label point.
Something else.
And so when I give the name to the class,
I'm committing to a particular semantics
and with names it's difficult to say this
is this is just a pair of two integers.
OK, so tuples.
This great ability to represent just a
pair of integers or a pair of something
or a triple.
Of course you can go on and on and this
is a triple of integers or.
Let's move out from 2 integers and a
float, et cetera, et cetera. OK,
so ML in this respect was a first,
one of the first in introducing this idea
of tuples that were really natural given
the mathematical root of the programming
language.
Because in mathematics this is fairly
natural.
It's just the cross product of sets of
values.
And I mean it's OK Now the problem is
that if I have a point, I can say P dot X.
Or P dot Y and I can refer to the single.
Fields. Um, so let me give a.
One point. Oh,
in functional programming languages.
So in the standard programming language,
when you invoke a function,
you get the result.
OK,
what if you need several vendors of the
result of the function? OK,
there could be random situations where
you need this,
then either you need an object with with
the etcetera,
or in several languages you can exploit
the global variables.
Or set effects of the function. OK,
the function of the tags the value,
but also sets some global variable which
is accessible by the caller.
In this way you can pass more information
to the caller.
In function department this is not
possible because functions.
Most of the clean functional programming
languages functions are pure and not from
a set of vector.
Therefore the only way to return more
than one value is to group them
substructure.
So it is very natural to use status in
the second.
Absolutely. Uh.
Now this will be a rather philosophical
class,
so be prepared because I will try to push
you in thinking about a lot about of the
syntax,
which is something that I started
introducing yesterday.
With respect to the interaction of
different syntaxes,
because if you like tuples,
tuples are not for free because if I type
E dot,
I mean we know that this language is
compiled, statically typed.
Strongly typed with static coping and
blah and blah,
and it's also high order and so because
we know there is a.net language,
we know that the runtime is.net,
so we know that everything is an object.
Because that is uh uh the the the runtime
uh uh core value so um.
By accident,
if you type in dot tab in the common line
you you got a nice completion and so as
you can see you have get type to string
equals get ash code get type.
That's it. OK,
so you have no fields to retrieve one of
the two arguments,
which makes sense because how can give a
name which is OK for everyone to the 1st
and to the 2nd?
Field.
So the traditional in in F in ML is to
have a function which say OK the first of
P is 1 and then there is also sorry there
is also a second of P which is the second
value and of course there is.
3rd, 4th,
I mean it would be an infinite number of
function.
So at some point there is the end and no.
You are the mic. I think that.
And no, I mean well, OK.
How I do I get the the the component of
123?
I guess that's from the context that
should guess that I'm meaning in in F
sharp. OK,
I don't remember the name of the function
because I don't use it that much.
Come on, I will see you soon.
That is point.
Is there a function beyond is so unfair
first and SMD?
Like proof that no man remembers all the
I mean I work it to the compiler.
Oh, there are no uh, OK.
O.
Apparently there is no. Oh,
that's interesting.
And so maybe an answer is in a in ML,
you know, in a camel and is no,
there is no port in in in F#.
That's interesting, you see,
even mix the language.
Great, nice example. Having said that,
the natural way to extract,
I mean you can, it will be really,
really not that useful to have a function
which takes.
A tuple value and the number of the field
that is called array or structure. OK,
so the natural way which the I spoiled me.
Is to use a function of the language that
is called pattern matching.
Again, pattern matching.
So if I say let ABC.
Equal 123. Guess what?
A evaluates to 1 to evaluate to two B.
Sorry evaluates to 2C23. So in.
Pattern matching basically is a very nice
feature that was introduced and now is
available for sure in C#,
but I think it's been used also in other
languages.
Basically the idea is I give you.
I I know that the right side of my
assignment as a a given structure.
In terms of a tuple and I pattern match
by giving names one to the 1st and this
can be very complicated in C#.
This is the maximum you can get because
tuples are available in the language but.
7.
Here you can you can you can go farther
and say OK if I have a tuple of tuples
which in fact is a tree.
And now the pattern matching becomes much
more interesting because.
This tree has so the tuple has three
elements. The first element is 1,
the second element is a tuple which
contains 2 and string A,
and then there is the third element with
this tree.
And here on the left I gave exactly the
same structure and I gave name to all the
components and so I was able to extract
all the values.
So pattern matching is very very powerful
because it allows to decompose the
structure of a value.
Into its constituent by using the
structure of the value, not names.
So if you like tuples for the reasons
that we just introduced.
We all we also need a way to extract a
single value out of tuples and the
pattern matching is the right way to do.
2.
Now um.
Sometimes I may be interested just in the.
Oh,
in the second value of a type of a tuple
or notice that here I can also pattern
match in a different way.
I I mean to me a I'm interested in having
the three component of the tuple, so ABC.
And in this case, B is a tuple,
which is the second element,
which is the tuple of two and eight.
I can even say you know what I'm
interested only in the string. I mean,
I know the structure because I'm the
programmer and I did.
Why should I give a name which we said
that are expensive to maintain?
Since I'm interested only into the string
field,
I can use the under score which basically
is.
I'm not interested to give a name at this.
I know that there is something there but
I'm not interested to that and so if I
evaluate.
Wait, I get the a string. OK, so.
Going back to the original point,
F sharp is not using the brace syntax for
function invocation because it was
already been taken to express tuples. OK,
so if I write.
So notice I can write add XY equal X + y.
And in this case add how many argument
have as the add function.
Only one which is a tuple and in fact if
we look at the signature of the function.
Add is a function that takes int.
By int and returns int.
And the fact that I use X&
Y in this case technically is a pattern
matching and say this function takes as
input one value which is a pair.
The first component of the pair,
I name it X,
the second component of the pair and name
it Y.
And then I use that perfect flat odd XY
we said is.
Let me rewrite here because it's.
Easier. Um.
Add XYX plus Y.
In this case this function has two
arguments.
But if you remember mathematical
definition of a function,
functions in mathematics are defined in
multiple ways.
You can even define functions in terms of
relations.
Uh, certainly you can say.
Add is a function that if you give me an
integer.
It returns a function which given another
integer, it will return an integer.
This is interesting because I can define
another function like this.
So.
What happens if I write in two?
I call the ink, so increment.
Apart from having used the the ink name,
the point is that the syntax of ML
allowed.
Everyone to specify arguments to a
function from left to right,
one at a time. So the language tells you.
You know what?
Given if you give me the first argument,
I will give you back a function.
So when I write the add 1 to I can also
write the same expression like this.
And this is strange.
So this phenomenon, this feature,
this call it whatever you want it is
known as curry.
So that in the language all the function
technically takes only one argument.
And this is possible because the language
is.
So to speak,
more I am better than being able to
return a function in C.
So because in this case you are
generating, so so to speak,
a new function from an existing function.
So you are not returning a function which
is a code block or a Lambda in JavaScript,
which is just a selector of function.
You are given a function obtaining a new
function.
Thanks to the curing ability.
Hm.
And this expression here exemplify
exactly this because through the
parentheses I applied one which is the
first argument the system.
So if I evaluate the one,
I get a new function which as you can see
gets an internal name because the
compilers compiles,
obtain bytecode and prepares for the
execution. So technically.
There are generated.
There is a generated code behind this,
but nevertheless this function.
So the result of evaluating one add one
is a function that from int returns an
integer.
So it's an operation that allows me,
given any function,
to create another function.
OK.
Why this is useful?
Oh,
there are a lot of programming patterns
that benefit from the curring, so.
If you write a function, I don't know.
Let me invent read DB.
You will require a connection and I don't
know table name.
OK.
Um.
We will later explore the signature of
function. Nevertheless, Read DB is a.
A function that takes 2 arguments and I'm
conveying you by the name that I'm it's a
function that is a DB.
It requires a variable that is the
connection and then the name of the table.
But when you work with a database it it
is fairly natural.
To reuse the same connection ever and
ever. So it is so natural to say OK,
let read table equal so table name equal.
Read DB.
Of a specific connection, I need that con.
A connection is likely to be a string or
an object.
I'm using a string and so read table.
Um, table name equal read DB con.
So in in this way.
Readtable will work by assing the table
name.
Oh.
OK, fair enough.
Thank.
The evaluation requires that I evaluate
the full block in a single statement
because otherwise the type inference will
not work.
So given the the the single statement,
the the compiler wasn't unable to type
check everything yet and so gather that.
Given the fact that it it is a void
function, it's OK.
Read table A basically says OK,
I'm interested in reading the table name
A and I'm in in my part of the code that
I'm unaware that inside read table the.
Connection has been fixed by someone else.
OK,
so in configuration this is a typical
pattern that you use all around your code.
So basically you specify from left to
right function to making a more general
function down to a more specific function.
This is a a a trait, but as I was saying,
we were saying everything in a
PROGRAMMING language implies some every
design.
Impose some uh.
Cost and some assumption. OK,
so the price you have to pay is.
Like me.
One minute.
Times.
Alright.
Yeah, mine's fine.
So whenever I define a function,
the cost I have to pay is that I I never
will get unless I want.
A fixed number of arguments.
In that case I can use a tuple as we we
shown at some point using that case and
say this function takes exactly 1
argument and this argument is a tuple.
Otherwise you have to live with this idea
that function takes.
Are unary in the sense that they take
always one argument,
and if you specify multiple arguments,
basically it is a function that takes one
argument gives you back another function
with the remaining arguments to fix.
Any questions?
OK, at some point I.
Define the.
The Readb function with two arguments and.
Honey, I've got an interesting signature.
So unit is like void because I didn't
want to specify the body,
so I returned the empty expression and
this other special value which is unit no
value. OK, it's like void in C.
So this last, it's easy.
Um.
The first argument on has been labeled as
stick A.
You know that this is a generic function.
Why?
I I saw a lot of hands.
And what is the implication by the fact
that no type has been specified?
Perfect so.
Let define this swap function that takes
as input A&B and returns B&A.
Oops, sorry, new.
What is the type of this?
OK, you're right,
but let me change the name.
Otherwise we get.
Ish.
BC OK,
because ML names generic type from A,
so it would have been a nightmare.
So the type is.
I take one argument which is a tuple of
type A&B because.
The language has no more information to
say to tell.
From the user I did.
The type of CMD.
So the only thing that you can say, OK,
you give me as long as TK type will be
used where TK type is accepted.
For me it's fine.
And the same applies to B tick B.
This means that I can say swap.
1/2.
And I add to one.
Question.
Do you think that this will work?
Yes,
because the definition will bind the
string type to the TK and the int type to
the TB.
And the output it will be in the string,
so it works. Now this is interesting so.
It is like.
If I have defined 2 functions,
one function from given int int gives me
back a pair of int to give me back a pair
of insert and another function that.
String in gives back apparel in string.
So technically I defined a class of
functions.
That is a generic function.
And that is a specific form of typing
that is known as parametric polymorphism.
So polymorphism in PROGRAMMING language
refers to.
The ability of defining the semantic of
something that may change its polymorph
may change over time depending on how you
use it inheritance.
Is the form of polymorphism that you know
the best.
You know that wherever Class B is
expected,
any instance of a class inherited by
Class B will be accepted.
So you it is polymorph because.
You have uh uh elements of a direct class
that can are using the as elements of the
base class.
Parametric polymorphism is another form
of polymorphism,
and this is a way to look at it.
But at the same time you can also think
with the swap definition that I gave here
I generate in fact.
An infinite number of functions because
you have all the possible types as the
first type argument and the second type
argument.
And so whenever I write swap with a pair
of two types, technically.
It is like the compiler is generating a
specific version of swap function to
generate the result.
So as a matter of fact,
when we when you use curing,
you have a mean.
To take a function and create a new
function which is not just if this then
this function,
otherwise this other function possibly
with a closure,
which is something that we did until
today, but we basically transformed.
A function by creating a new function
with a different signature.
We refine the function when we define
this warp.
It is like as if we did define a class of
functions where I give you the schema and
and every time you activate the function
with a specific pair you get.
The particular function that works with
the types that I used.
Without this mechanism,
I I mean in in C this is not possible.
I mean in CI need to define swap int and
swap string int and so on and so forth.
So it is like.
I'm generating a function that is not
available.
I'm defining a class of functions with
those are perfect.
These these mechanisms is perfect.
For instance,
when you develop algorithms like sorting
where I mean you don't really pay
attention to the value,
you want to just change the order of
things, move things around.
Whatever the thing is,
sometimes you may want to say, OK,
I need a number. OK, so not not now,
but in the future we will see that there
is in polymorphic parametric polymorphism.
It is possible to indicate.
So type constraints. So you say OK,
swope takes two value of this part with
this constraint, not any type,
but in the purest form.
So in terms of the high order programming.
The interesting thing is that you can
basically create functions out of other
function that are not just specifying A
blocking line.
As you are using to if you're a
JavaScript programmer or C#, Java, Java,
Java's Lambda, yes,
except I mean in pretty much all the
programming languages we are using to see.
The arrow syntax for having lambdas and
you think that that that that's it. No,
that's a very simple form of high order
manipulation. You can divide,
you can devise operation that allows you
to manipulate the code.
And then compile it.
Because of course in JavaScript.
What do you do when you need the
JavaScript interpreter?
12 in a browser.
You open the console.
And you have a JavaScript interpreter.
In JavaScript I can do something similar
because I can always say.
Eval 1 + 2.
OK,
I deserve that it is blocking inside the
browser for security reason.
But I mean in in interpreted languages,
typically you have a beautiful function
which is called eval.
Eval takes as input a string and you get
as a result the evaluation of that string.
OK, so.
If I can evaluate a string,
I can define a function so I can generate
the string with the definition of the
function,
which is an arbitrary function definition.
I evaluate and the result will be the
function. OK so.
In interpreted languages,
many of the things that I'm discussing
right now,
and if I'm not part of the language,
you can work around,
you can generate the string of the
program and evaluate,
and you get whatever you want, OK.
Of course it's not type safe in any
possible way.
You may introduce syntax errors,
semantics error, etcetera.
So in the higher order programming
languages,
compiled higher order programming
languages.
Research is looking for operation that
can be implemented in an efficient way.
So the operations such as curing,
such as generics, functions, etc.
Are there and you can use them being sure
that they can be compiled quite
efficiently,
so the resulting code will be as fast as
AC code or.
Other programming language code.
Any questions?
So ML was called ML,
which stands for Meta language because
basically it allowed to twist the
programming language syntax.
And semantics by.
Using specific operators and not just say
OK,
generate the string with the ML program
and then evaluate.
You can basically change the semantics by
using a number of mechanisms in the
language. One of these are.
Uh, curving and uh.
Uh, there are other mechanism.
These are uh.
Still bound to.
Functional high order functional
programming languages that are mechanisms
that allows you to basically.
Overload names in the language. Mm-hmm.
So yesterday we.
Uh,
I introduced something that now I can do
better.
FX.
Now I can also show the typing of this
thing.
So forward pipe as it is called this
operator is a function that they can
decay.
Generic type and a function that takes
tick A and gives back tick B returns
ticks tick B. If you remember,
basically it's a way to invert the
function and the argument.
OK,
so you specify instead of giving the
function name and then the argument,
you do the opposite.
So I can do one for word pipe Inc.
And this is also this also witness how
complicated can become to read.
O.
Attention.
The fact that you can use the forward
pipe syntax, which yesterday recommended,
is a nice syntax because it can give this
streaming left to right way of writing
function application which is more
natural to us at least in the Western
world.
I will,
I I don't know for Arabs if it's or in
Japanese it's the same,
but nevertheless we tend to read left,
left to right.
So it is easier for us to read argument
and then what you want to do with the
argument and that's the thing.
Notice that this is a useful definition
only for one reason,
because in F sharp YAML all the function
have exactly one argument.
Otherwise the forward pipe operator will
be impossible to define.
So I hope you start appreciating how all
the element,
the syntax element and the design choice
that are behind.
Like programming language design interact
one with the other because this
particular pattern is useful only if you
have curry because only then you can say
OK take if you have an argument and a
function and apply the function to the
argument because all the function have
exactly 1.
Otherwise,
I will need a definition for every given
a function with one argument,
given a function with two arguments,
and so on and so and so forth. OK,
so this is a typical example of
interaction.
Uh of these Uh mechanics and of course
this allow me to also to write ink.
And in this case I get 3 and so on
because and of course this is if I want
right.
Straighter that that's the same thing,
but clearly for us it's easy to to to to
be read the 1st way rather than the 2nd
way.
This it it it is really more intuitive.
OK.
So high order function programming
languages give you more than one way to
manipulate high order values that are
functions.
This is a form of meta programming.
Because in fact you are sort of
generating a portion of your program
because the function typically is
declared and is defining the program
itself.
OK,
so the fact that you've got operators
that allows you to manipulate the
function, it's more than. I mean,
of course you do the same with integers,
but that's a different thing because the
domain of integers is the final side of
the language and your operator in the
language that allows.
To manipulated integers.
But when I derive the increment function
from the the add function,
basically I generated the new function by
using an existing one.
Dynamically and I even changed the number
of arguments,
the additive of the of the function. OK,
and this is possible mostly because of
the in this case of the Lambda calculus
nature of of the language.
So don't think moral of the story.
Every story is a moral moral of the story.
Don't think that functions are all high
order programming function.
I order programming languages are only
those where the you can return a value
from from a function because Pascal was
able to return a procedure or function
from another procedure or function,
but that didn't make.
It a high order programming language.
The same applies to C In C you can use
the function pointers,
but function pointer is not enough to
qualify C as a high order programming
language.
OK, then of course it's easier.
I don't know if you have something to say
around that,
but I think it's easier to to tell what
is not an I or different functional
programming language from because there
is this.
Common.
Is that you're able to manipulate
function as values.
But if I look several functional
programming languages,
the operation that you have to manipulate
function values are very different and
I'm not sure that I'm able to tell where
is the threshold.
Because I mean to me it's easy to say C
is not a functional programming language
even though I can return function pointer.
So it seems that that ability is not
enough.
I tell that JavaScript is a functional
programming language because I can return
a function.
That capture. So I have lexical closure.
I didn't mention them,
but of course the lexical closures is
part of the high of the programming.
But by thinking by now,
I'm not sure that I'm able to tell where
is the threshold.
One aspect certainly is the possibility
of defining.
Oh, yes, yeah. I mean, yeah, you're right.
I mean,
lexica closure seems to be a good
separation point.
Um.
Yeah,
the lexical closure is the minimum viable
set of features that defines A functional
programming language. But I'm not sure.
I mean,
I'm not sure that because these are the
operation that I've shown you that are
from ML.
If you take ask and you get these.
But you also get others,
and I'm pretty sure that there are some
unknown to me programming languages that
do different things even than that. OK,
so.
Functions are a way to manipulate
programs.
You can basically have a program that
defines some way part of itself depending
on the execution,
because depending on the execution you
can get a function or another and.
Then the behavior will change of your
program.
So it's a form of metaprogramming to some
extent because you manipulate the
language. In other programming languages,
these things are.
Have consequences.
So uh, some one thing that is.
It's not for all high order programming
languages, but it's.
And important to know is.
I'm not sure that I'm able to write any
more abstract code in one line.
Let me try.
Yes, that's one.
Oh, no, no.
No, he's gone.
No.
Sorry.
So I did install that on.
You just recall that you're not IOI,
which is the F track integration in just
recorded,
but I found out that I wasn't able to do
to enroll the F track interactive and so
that's the reason because I reverted to
the terminal, but it's not that calm.
Oh, for the ball too.
No, that's not.
This one.
Thank you.
I don't know why, not from Anna.
Ha.
OK.
Give me one second there.
OK.
This video.
This was the code I was about to write OK.
So something that characterize some of
the IO Gramming language is the ability
to reason about specific data structures
that have.
Particular.
Structure that I introduced the SMB when
I was I was talking about the numeric and
C Darper as an example of sophistication
in the compilation of the dish Sugaring
in the language.
OK.
But there was more than just the
sophisticated form of the sugaring.
Yesterday I focused myself on the fact
that the syntax of that particular amount
of code of C#.
The the semantics of how the the
semantics of that particular fragment of
C# code that was given in terms of a
class, etcetera.
But the concept that lies behind that is
much more interesting and sophisticated.
Because basically it gives you the
ability to express and reason and work
with sequences, sequences or.
Frequencies or.
So in general I have a domain of values.
I can say OK, if you give me a sequence,
I can operate on every element of the
sequence.
I give you back a sequence so I can move
from the domain of values.
In this case of the sequence of integers,
I can manipulate.
Each integer and give you back a sequence.
This is a typical form of programming.
So let's look at these.
And I don't think that we will be able to
dig into this syntax today,
so we'll do it on Monday.
But let me introduce this and let's spend
the the the final part of the the class
in commenting first this syntax.
Then we'll see how in F# and this is F#
is not ML.
Uh, you can find the uh.
Multiple. Uh,
you can personalize your syntax.
By changing.
The the label here OK.
Let's start with the sequences,
which is an easy one.
The only thing that I want to like to
point you out is that this is not a
keyword. This is an object. OK,
so the sequence object takes.
This argument which specify what you want
to do with the sequence.
So you you are building a sequence.
I didn't tell you at the beginning
functional, Andrea told you. In fact,
functional programming languages love to
be pure.
So by default,
whenever you you you introduce a name
that is redominute.
And that made the really popular
functional programming languages at the
end of the 80s when parallel programming
became interesting because race condition.
And so mutable state,
as Andrea was pointing out in the last
Rust class,
is due to the fact that the code can make
into the memory.
And so if you have multiple threads,
one on writing the same location and
there is a conflict.
If everything is read only, guess what?
No problem. Everything is read only.
You can go and write and write.
And of course you use the definition of a
name as the assignment.
Or when you assign to a function,
you copy and you assign the value.
Of the actual arguments to the formal
parameters,
and so you keep going by copying values
around.
It is not really possible to do an
interesting programming and efficient
programming in a pure form.
Mathematically you can,
but practically it's not really useful.
So the solution in some programming
languages was OK.
I made it really difficult for you to
have a mutable state, so in ML.
If you say let mutable then that that is
a variable.
If you see simply say let X equal that is
read only. OK,
so in this case I introduce A variable
because I need to a counter so that
mutable.
The alternative would have been read,
but it's OK. So this is very similar,
not to say equivalent to what I wrote
yesterday was true do ill.
It's.
It's it's incremented.
A voice through. OK, so.
This is not compiled into a fine state
automata as the C# compiling fence,
actually the sequence.
Object as a fixed number of operands,
typical of monadic expressions.
And so by implementing those,
so this the compiler basically takes the
block and transforms the block into a
number of operations in this sequence
object that gives you back.
Basically we have to find the automata in
this case. OK, so now I can say SEC take.
Uh.
Sorry and.
So take Google.
Now we know that for Y operator N is a
sequence of integers.
And I use a a function that is available
in the module sequencer.
It allows me to extract the first two
elements I can say.
The first.
1000 numbers and I can extract.
It's interesting, uh.
Also to see.
The the difference of syntaxes less I
should have the notepad of yesterday
class because.
I'm up.
Hmm.
They would have out.
It's not this. Uh, uh, OK, well,
I've seen it.
So.
So for years I I've I've used the notepad
because at every crash of my system all
the notes were deleted and I was happy.
Then Microsoft introduced the auto saving
notes.
I hate it. No, this is not. So this is.
Oh, sensitive.
This is not. This is not.
I don't remember where I where I wrote it
out. No, sorry, it was in Chagikiti.
That's the reason because it's too
complicated to find the the the place.
But I hope you remember how I did write
the C part of the code.
It was if you remember.
I enumerable of the integer and and then
the function and then the coding was like
it was pretty similar,
but the perception of the meaning of the
code it was very different because in
what does it mean in C#?
That a function returns an enumeration
and then the enumeration is not an
interface,
so the result should be either something
that generates an enumerable.
But it can't be the definition of
denomination.
You need a a class which implements the
interface.
So it was really creepy to read that code.
I still remember the first time I did it.
I appreciate the the functionality,
but I mean it was wrong to some extent.
It's much more natural to do this thing.
Oh, by the way,
I forgot to stress the arrow assignment
in mathematical.
Friendly programming languages is never
done with equal. Equal is a comparison,
it's not assignment.
It was C that imposed us the assignment
using equal.
So here is X + 1 is assigned to it apart
from that.
So the sequence as you can see defines.
If we need data structure,
that's the main point that I didn't want
to express it in the main meetings.
Because there is the while through and we
learn that we can sort of suspend the
execution,
return the value and then restart the
execution. Why this is important?
Because this allows us to represent.
An infinite data structure in our program.
Because N represents all the integer
numbers and then it's up to me to unroll
the sequence as much as I want.
But if I ask for more.
1,000,000 OK, it's there.
Call.
I can use it.
And if I can.
And I can um.
Take the sequence,
use the the sequence inside another
sequence so I can define let B equal
sequence.
Uh.
For each.
Hmm.
I'm not sure.
Uh, and in an.
Um.
Return to.
Uh.
It's too long since I really programmed F
sharp and I you can see it.
Um.
Let me ask.
I was able to take the sun, obviously.
Or OK, no, there was a no, no parenthesis.
You see, I'm.
Or an in an.
OK, do.
Oh.
No, this is not recorded.
When you know too many languages,
you tend to mix one and the other quite
easily anyway, so.
I can um.
Enumerate the end sequence and return
another sequence as part of the original
sequence and so.
You you are able to define how to
transform a sequence into another
sequence by.
Processing every element in the sequence
and return another sequent as a result.
Set bake 2.
I.
02 and twice. OK,
so it's interesting because this object
that would dig into on Monday the
sequence object.
Is an object that basically allows me to
manipulate the sequences and not just
single values.
That's a feature that allows you to
express complex notions such as infinite
data structure,
and you can even manipulate the infinite
data structure through the statement
operations.
And I think we're done for today.
Have a nice weekend and see you on Monday.
OK.